Let me introduce to you Rezero.
دعوني أقدم لكم ريزيرو.
This little fellow was developed
هذا الزميل الصغير تم تطويره
by a group of 10 undergraduate students
من طرف مجموعة من 10 طلبة جامعيين
at the Autonomous Systems Laboratory
في مختبر أنظمة التحكم الذاتي
at ETH-Zurich.
في ETH - زيوريخ.
Our robot belongs to a family of robots
روبوتنا ينتمي إلى عائلة روبوتات
called Ballbots.
تسمى بالبوت.
Instead of wheels, a Ballbot is balancing
بدل العجلات، يتوازن البالبوت
and moving on one single ball.
ويتحرك على كرة واحدة.
The main characteristics of such a system is
أهم خصائص نظام كهذا هو
that there's one sole contact point to the ground.
أنه هناك نقطة اتصال واحدة بالأرض.
This means that the robot
يعني هذا أن الروبوت
is inherently unstable.
بطبيعته غير مستقر.
It's like when I am trying to stand
وكأنني أحاول الوقوف
on one foot.
على قدم واحدة.
You might ask yourself, what's the usefulness
قد تسألون أنفسكم، ما الفائدة
of a robot that's unstable?
من روبوت غير مستقر؟
Now we'll explain that in a second.
الآن سنشرح هذا في لحظة.
Let me first explain how Rezero
دعوني أشرح أولا كيف أن ريزيرو
actually keeps his balance.
يحافظ فعلا على توازنه.
Rezero keeps his balance by constantly
ريزيرو يحافظ على توازنه بمواصلة
measuring his pitch angle with a sensor.
قياس زاوية التأرجح من خلال جهاز استشعار.
He then counteracts and avoids toppling over
ثم يستجيب لذلك ويتجنب السقوط
by turning the motors appropriately.
من خلال إدارة المحركات بشكل مناسب.
This happens 160 times per second,
يحدث هذا 160 مرة في الثانية،
and if anything fails in this process,
وإن فشل أي شيء في هذه العملية،
Rezero would immediately fall to the ground.
ريزيرو سيسقط فورا على الأرض.
Now to move and to balance,
الآن للتحرك والتوازن،
Rezero needs to turn the ball.
يحتاج ريزيرو إلى إدارة الكرة.
The ball is driven by three special wheels
الكرة مدفوعة بثلاثة عجلات خاصة
that allow Rezero to move into any direction
تسمح لريزيرو بالتحرك في أي اتجاه
and also move around his own axis
وكذلك بالتحرك حول محوره الخاص
at the same time.
في نفس الوقت.
Due to his instability, Rezero is always
بسبب عدم استقراره، يكون ريزيرو دائما
in motion. Now here's the trick.
في تحرك. الآن ها هي الحيلة.
It's indeed exactly this instability that allows
فعدم الاستقرار بالفعل هو ما يسمح
a robot to move very [dynamically].
للروبوت بالتحرك بشكل حيوي للغاية.
Let's play a little.
دعونا نلعب قليلا.
You may have wondered what happens
قد تتساءلون ما الذي يحصل
if I give the robot a little push.
إن قمت بدفع الروبوت قليلا.
In this mode, he's trying to maintain
بهذه الطريقة، هو يحاول الحفاظ على
his position.
وضعيته.
For the next demo, I'd like you to introduce
في العرض الموالي، أود أن أقدم لكم
to my colleagues Michael, on the computer,
زملائي مايكل على الحاسوب،
and Thomas who's helping me onstage.
وتوماس الذي سيساعدني على الخشبة.
In the next mode, Rezero is passive,
في النسق الموالي، سيكون ريزيرو سلبيا،
and we can move him around.
ويمكننا أن نحركه.
With almost no force I can control
بدون أدنى قوة يمكنني التحكم في
his position and his velocity.
موضعه وسرعنه.
I can also make him spin.
يمكنني كذلك جعله يدور.
In the next mode, we can get Rezero
في النسق الموالي، يمكننا أن نجعل ريزيرو
to follow a person.
يتبع شخصا.
He's now keeping a constant distance to Thomas.
هو الآن يحافظ على مسافة ثابتة من توماس.
This works with a laser sensor
يعمل هذا بمستشعر لايزر
that's mounted on top of Rezero.
موضوع أعلى ريزيرو.
With the same method, we can also
بنفس الطريقة، يمكننا كذلك
get him to circle a person.
أن نجعله يدور على شخص.
We call this the orbiting mode.
نسمي هذا النسق المداري.
All right, thank you, Thomas.
حسنا، شكرا لك توماس.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Now, what's the use of this technology?
الآن، ما هي استخدامات هذه التكنولوجيا؟
For now, it's an experiment, but let me
في الوقت الحالي، إنها تجربة، لكن دعوني
show you some possible future applications.
أعرض عليكم بعض التطبيقات المستقبيلة.
Rezero could be used in exhibitions or parks.
ريزيرو يمكن أن يستخدم في المعارض أو المنتزهات.
With a screen it could inform people or show
من خلال شاشة، يمكنه أن يعلم الناس أو يأخذهم
them around in a fun and entertaining way.
في جولة بطريقة ممتعة ومرحة.
In a hospital, this device could be used to
في مستشفى، هذا الجهاز يمكن أن يستخدم
carry around medical equipment.
لنقل المعدات الطبية.
Due to the Ballbot system, it has a very small
بسبب نظام البالبوت، لديه موطئ قدم صغير للغاية
footprint and it's also easy to move around.
ومن السهل كذلك التنقل به.
And of course, who wouldn't like
وبالطبع، من قد يمانع
to take a ride on one of these.
في ركوب واحدة من هذه.
And these are more practical applications.
وهذه تطبيقات أكثر عملية.
But there's also a certain beauty
لكن هناك كذلك جمالية خاصة
within this technology.
داخل هذه التكنولوجيا.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.